Guide to the International History of Photography collection, 1885-1951
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
International History of Photography collection 1885-1951
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Rubenstein Library.
3.0 linear feet Extent: 10 Items
Collection dates from 1885-1951 and comprises ten vintage photographic prints by individuals considered to be master photographers. The prints are intended to represent major formats, techniques, and genres of the 19th and 20th centuries. Photographers whose prints are in the collection hail from Europe, the United States, and Mexico: Eugène Atget (printed by Berenice Abbot), Alvin Langdon Coburn, Manuel Alvarez Bravo, F. Holland Day, Peter Henry Emerson, Lewis Hine, Aaron Siskind, Ralph Steiner, Alfred Stieglitz, and Minor White. Formats range from photogravures to gelatin silver prints, with the latter predominating; all are black-and-white and matted. Subjects include rural landscapes, individual and group portraits, and urban streetscapes. Acquired by the Archive for Documentary Arts at Duke University.
RL.00641
Language: Material inEnglish
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. However, the prints cannot be photocopied or reproduced.
Researchers must wear gloves when handling the matted prints. Prints should always be picked up and supported with two hands. The prints cannot be removed from the mats, but researchers may open the window mat to see the full print. The Visual Materials Archivist must be consulted prior to any display of the photographs.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The prints in the International History of Photography collection were purchased by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from 2002-2008.
Collection Overview
The International History of Photography collection dates from 1885-1951 and comprises ten vintage photographic prints by individuals considered to be master photographers. The prints in this collection were acquired and assembled by the Rubenstein library staff, in part to provide students the opportunity to view and study original works from the world's foremost photographers as well as to learn about the major formats, techniques, and genres of the 19th and 20th centuries. Photographers whose prints are in the collection hail from Europe, Mexico, and the United States: Eugène Atget (printed by American photographer Berenice Abbot), Alvin Langdon Coburn, Manuel Alvarez Bravo, F. Holland Day, Peter Henry Emerson, Lewis Hine, Aaron Siskind, Ralph Steiner, Alfred Stieglitz, and Minor White. The print by Eugène Atget, Flower Man, was printed by well-known American photographer Berenice Abbot, who purchased part of Atget's negative archive in 1928. Formats range from photogravures to gelatin silver prints, with the latter predominating; all are black-and-white and are matted. Subjects include rural landscapes, individual and group portraits, and urban streetscapes.
Researchers must wear gloves when handling the prints. Prints should always be picked up and supported with two hands. The prints cannot be removed from the mats, but researchers may open the window mat to see the full print. The Visual Materials Archivist must be consulted prior to any display of the photographs.
Acquired by the Archive for Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Subject Headings
Abbott, Berenice, 1898-1991; Atget, Eugène, 1857-1927; Bravo, Manuel Alvarez, 1902-2002; Coburn, Alvin Langdon, 1882-1966; Day, F. Holland (Fred Holland), 1864-1933; Emerson, P. H. (Peter Henry), 1856-1936; Hine, Lewis Wickes, 1874-1940; Lewis, Wyndham, 1882-1957 -- Portraits; Siskind, Aaron; Steiner, Ralph, 1899-1986; Stieglitz, Alfred, 1864-1946; White, Minor; Documentary photography -- History; Photographers -- Europe; Photographers -- Mexico; Photographers -- United States; Photography -- History; Photography, Artistic -- History; Black-and-white photographs; Gelatin silver prints; Photogravures; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Contents of Collection
- International history of photography collection, 1886-1949, (3 boxes)
  All photographs are matted.
  - Alvin Langdon Coburn: Wyndham Lewis, 1916 Feb. 25, 6 1/8 x 8.5" photogravure, 11x14" mat (Box 1)
  - Lewis Hine: Young mill boys, Gastonia [N.C.], 1912 Oct. 23, 4.5 x 6.5" gelatin silver print, 11x14" mat (Box 1)
  - Peter Henry Emerson: Towing the Reed, published in "Life and Landscape on the Norfolk Broads (1886)," 1885, Platinum print, 16x20" mat (Box 1)
  - Minor White: Sandblaster, 1949 [San Francisco], 8.5 x 9 7/8" gelatin silver print, 11x14" mat (Box 2)
    Signed by photographer on front; edition 71/100.
  - Ralph Steiner: Untitled, circa 1930 [Row of seven 19th century houses in urban setting, cars parked out front.], Gelatin silver print, 11x14" mat (Box 2)
  - Aaron Siskind: North Carolina 30, 1951 (printed later), gelatin silver [Close-up of outdoor advertisements, tattered on side of unidentified building.], Gelatin silver print 11x14" mat (Box 2)
  - Alfred Stieglitz: Ploughing, 1904, 7.5 x 9.5" photogravure, 11x14" mat (Box 3)
    Image appeared in Stieglitz's journal Camera Work in Oct. 1905, the first issue devoted to Stieglitz's own photographs since its inception in 1903.
  - Eugène Atget: Flower Man, circa 1900-1910, printed by Berenice Abbot circa 1928, 6.5 x 9" gelatin silver print, 11x14" mat (Box 3)
    Stamped on retro: "photo E. Atget collection Berenice Abbot 1 W. 67th St."
  - Manuel Alvarez Bravo: Mayan child with Tulum, Mexico, 1942, Gelatin silver print, 11x14" mat (Box 3)
  - F. Holland Day: [Bust-length portrait of Cora Folsom, a Hampton College teacher], circa 1905, 7.75 x 9.75" photogravure, 11x14" mat (Box 3)
    Print is accompanied by photocopies of several letters from Folsom to Day regarding his visit to the campus, as well as photocopies of images of Folsom and pages from the Hampton yearbook. When acquired, print had small tear on right side.